well the the topic that uh
deeper brought up yesterday was death
and so i thought
what is the problem with death
what's the issue there
what is the issue
it's not wanted
at least what is perceived as
what that day so
why would it not be wanted by default
because it's seen as
losing the possibility of
engaging with things with things in a pleasurable
with things with things in a pleasurable
way
and why would that be
why would that be
important
because pleasure is valid so
so
death is then not wanted and unpleasant
only because interrupts the things that
we want
more or less yeah
so what will happen if there's nothing
that you want
would that still be a problem no no
no no
i don't know
and that's the whole
whether we spoke about the body and
possessions
and goes as deep as your sense organs
your body
not being developed in regard to the
body means
means
taking it up with yours means depending
on it
means wanting what it wants
means basically being within the sixth
sense space within sensuality
which means death it's um
it's going to be a problem because these
things are subjected to that cessation
interruption and ending
so then it's only your ownership
that makes you
be affected by that problem
if you disown if you abandon your eyes
ear nose
other senses
if the mind is fully withdrawn from
centrality sees the danger in it then
nothing that death affects can be
relevant to you
can cause you pain and that's the
dispassion this passion is the result of
practice this passion towards not getting rid of
this passion towards not getting rid of
things not like
managing them
whatever else no just being
dispassionate towards their arising
or ceasing doesn't matter
so how then to develop that discretion
how would one go about it
something else that's your strength
exactly
but what else
so
for most people when they start
sense restraining virtue would be just
kind of bearing the pain
but that's not the enduring we talk
about the endurance we talk about is on that
the endurance we talk about is on that
mental level of not acting out not
welcoming or delighting as the suitors
say
so bearing needs to come first yeah but
how do you endure things on the mental
level so it's not just
so it's not just
kind of mindless bearing like asceticism
how how can that become more
by developing understanding um
so what specifically like how would i do
that so i am bearing i'm keeping the
precepts and bearing the elements
but you know we talk about it doing
things on the right level all the time
not trying to get rid of them not
justifying them or managing them not
psychologizing them
so how do i learn to endure things on
that level
what what what can i look for where do i
look for that
because all i see is just bearing of the
pain what do i do within that
what do i do within that
if i'm not giving into the management
is there anything i can do there
wouldn't be the management how do i go
about it
seeing why these things are painful
sorry seeing why these things are
painful um
but that's that can also fall on the
level of management and explanation
so
is that what it would determine whether
i'm trying to manage my pain or whether
i'm enduring it on the right level so i
see its nature
what what determines the management
is it what i do
or how i do it
how or why i do it
so so that's how you look for whether
you're trying to get rid of things out
of your will basically
because whenever there is the
urge and pressure to manage the
uncomfortable mental states
that arise on their bare
bearing of the elements bearing of the
words of others bearing of the precepts
bearing of the sense restraint whenever
you try to manage means you implicitly
want to get rid of it which means
implicitly there is a version
and that's where you end up revolving
around it
and that's why i keep saying like it's
about not welcoming
which doesn't mean preventing you from
coming at my doorstep that's not within
my domain my domain is to not welcome
you and not delight in your presence
so how do i not delight in your presence
well i practice the non-delight while
you are present
but if i'm concerned about getting rid
of you because you know i blame you
for this disrupted mind
means i'm putting the problem where the
problem isn't
and the way to stop doing that is as we
often say to start actually practicing
mindfulness on top of the you know sense restraint
on top of the you know sense restraint
and during the virtue bearing the virtue
precepts and so on
mindfulness and self-questioning on the
level of uh why am i doing what i'm
doing including trying to manage my
dukkha so why am i doing it
so why am i doing it
is it because i just want to get rid of
this pain so how's that different from
craving against discomfort
aversion towards pain that just keeps
fueling everything else
so that's that right endurance
like you recognize it on the level so
it's not determined by what you do it's
determined by why you're doing it
because see somebody can say yes i
listen to these discussions and i
question myself but why oh because i
want to get rid of the pain right here
right now
i don't want to endure it on that mental
level and that means also you're using this as
and that means also you're using this as
just a way of managing your pain of
course everybody will start like that
but as long as you know
that that's not a practice they will
lead you to freedom from suffering it
will only result in managing the pain
then you can actually focus
on upgrading it then you will know that
there is an upgrade which is
not acting out of the mental state but
instead being able to endure it and when
the buddha's talked about it we
mentioned it yesterday
you know the suit about uh the master of
the thoughts
and the last ones that you know you
crush your mind with your mind and
people often think that ah i just get
get look repress whatever is it no you
crush your mind with your mind in other
words you don't go and get rid of the thoughts
you don't go and get rid of the thoughts
that your mind has
and mind as a sense does not appear on
the level of your attention in the
thought it's always the background so
you crush the background with the
background that's what that statement
says but when people read the mind they just
but when people read the mind they just
assume oh it's this thought of my mind
and i have that's what i crush so they
end up just like no no no no actually it
requires wisdom to see that to endure
the mind rightly on the level of the
background you need to see the signs of
the mind first
and that's not something you can attend
directly that's something you pick as
the background you know the simile of
the the king eating the food you see the
king you see the food you don't see
anything else
but you notice
that he seems to linger along
certain dishes
more he dismisses others
he dismisses others
on account of that
you see the background of that behavior
is his preference
oh he leans towards this if this is in
front he leans towards that if this is
in front
but you don't see the leaning you infer
it and you cannot measure it or or
objectify it because it's not it's not
visible but you can understand it if
you're skilled
as the skilled cook would infer the
preferences the signs and tokens of his
behavior unskill cook wouldn't he would just see
unskill cook wouldn't he would just see
what's in front of him touch move eat do
repeat he doesn't see anything else and
that's why there is no mind development
for such monk as it would have said in
that suit
so it comes down to knowing what you're
doing with like why you're doing what
you're doing
and constantly questioning that so it
will kind of pull you out of that need
pressure habit to manage dukkha because
that is the natural response craving
against discomfort
so you need to actually refrain from
acting out of that because it is your
will fundamentally it is your will
you're trying to get rid of the mental
states uh on the level of not like oh i try to
uh on the level of not like oh i try to
get rid of them in a sense eventually
i'm hoping to become another hand no i'm
trying to get rid of it means i'm trying
to antidote whatever is currently
bothering me
that's basically just action reaction
just responding with ill will towards
what's unpleasant
so mindfulness of death is
one way of defining that could be to see
the sign of death
exactly so even when people do the
practice of mindfulness of death it
becomes like
this sort of contrived again antidoting
responding managing doing this if it's
left and move right if it's right to
move no it's recognizing the context and
then see what is the what are the signs
and tokens of your liability to death
where is the danger there you realize
you can't even conceive
how it would be if there were no death
it's just you can't even imagine that
yet here you are acting as if death
won't come your way why is that that's
not going to be
measured by your eyes and nose and so on
and your sensations
exactly it's a part of the context so as
we said before it's that ownership
oh it's because
things i own
ownership i assumed things i've taken
for the sake of pleasure always for the
sake of safety comfort all of that
that's why death is a problem that's why
i fear it that's why i avoid it that's
why i turn a blind eye to it
so what if i relinquish my acquisitions
as a suitors would say
then oh that is not a problem i have
gone beyond death
that which is subjected to battle and
destruction these five aggregates that's
it that's not my problem anymore when
that breaks apart that's part of the
binary
so in other words you don't need to
and this is true for most all of the
contemplations in a way you don't need
to do the contemplation of death you
just have to discern what's already
there that's liable to it
and uh
why are you not giving it up
as simple as that and it goes down to
eye ear nose senses
it's not just the question of
your material objects of the senses that
you possess it's the whole domain
and how can you give up your eyes can
you just pull them out in the same sense
you would throw your favorite thing no
so that's that recognizing of the
background and that um
well discernment the summit of ownership
of that necessary basis for your
experience so developing this passion
towards your body
can i ask a question about
because on that
you know every you think in the
beginning like i want to be free from suffering i
like i want to be free from suffering i
don't want to die i want to be
not liable to death anymore so i want to
go beyond death because
i want to be also free from suffering
that's the sort of
be free from suffering or be free from
death without
basically relinquishing
yourself which is why which is what death is in a
which is why which is what death is in a
way the fact that like i won't be
so
it's hard to
practice towards that
while also because i mean in a way
nibbana or the the idea
from the beginning of nirvana is like
myself will not be that's almost what
death is
for you so it's almost like kind of
you're aiming towards what you're afraid
of
so how do you
well that's the that's like the um
craving is to be abandoned by the means
of craving conceit by the means of
conceit so yes you have to want it first
which means it's going to be rooted in
craving either craving for pleasure of
either craving for pleasure of
liberation or craving out of the
aversion towards pain
so that's what directs you towards
learning the dharma
but if you actually practice towards the
if you actually practice towards the
right view
you get to realize that aha craving is
the root of the problem
not a a
lack of
satisfaction of my desires like in other
words not because i didn't get what i
want it's because of this rooted bonding
so now you get to understand the middle
way that the buddha was teaching as a
result of which you become aware of your
intentions you don't fuel you don't
welcome you don't delight the ones that
are rooted in greed aversion delusion
even if it's you know craving to get rid
of the dukkha because that's the
practice oh you know that's the
management which means practice is
second primarily i want to get rid of
the pain
you stop doing that through that
discernment and then
you will be free from craving so yes on
account of your initial craving you have
actually learned how to do things
rightly and stop fuel the craving
through acting out of craving
so as the buddha says in that suture
craving has been abandoned by the means
of craving
and same for the conceit i want to be
enlightened and be free from suffering
and because of that like if you keep
revolving around that and you never see
the root of that i want and that craving
and that aversion to its pain you won't
be free from suffering you'll just be
fueling your craving further
but as i said if you meet the right
instruction and have developed the
recognition of the background and the
signs of your mind which is what you
only somehow is
then you will get to see that middle
ground where aha
yes craving directed me to learn about
this but now i need to abandon this very
craving so not do things that are rooted
in craving
no welcome no delight endure it
on that level
not just bear it but endure it endure
the mental intention having recognized
it
and not try to get rid of it because
it's unpleasant
not certainly act out of it because it's
unpleasant so that's how you will stop
so that's how you will stop
uh cultivating aversion towards pain
and your craving is factually
diminishing then
this is it back to that
why is death a problem
because i think
well i know for a fact
from seeing other people's bodies
you know inferring my own that it's
going to fall apart it's it's for sure
uncertain and it will
and it will
fall apart
and that's going to
most likely feel very unpleasant getting
sick feels unpleasant you know breaking
your arm
not being able to use your body it feels
unpleasant so
it is going to fall apart
there is going to be some
disagreeability discomfort and pain
there and that is inevitable
and that is inevitable
and the problem is that i don't want to
feel that
but i can't just you know cancel out feeling
i can't just you know cancel out feeling
i can't just
kill the body
and escape that pain escape that falling
apart so the problem that i i see is that that
so the problem that i i see is that that
which we read about many times the
identification with the body
like taking the feelings personally
taking the body personally
that's the that's the issue there
because if that identification is not there
if that identification is not there
there is still a body
and that body will still fall apart
so if that identification is not there
that taking it personally is not there
then there is no problem
that body is just not mine anymore
it's just another body
you know why is pascal's body not my
concern because i don't take it personally
because i don't take it personally
so likewise with this one
so how do you not take it personally
by
restraining virtue and you know feeling that
virtue and you know feeling that
pressure and not taking that pressure
personally actually can't seeing it there i didn't
actually can't seeing it there i didn't
create that pressure here it is right
and
so what you're going to do what is the
symptom what is the symptom of taking
the pressure personally
what is well of course pressure is
suffering but what is the
how can you yeah exactly acting on
acting out trying to manage your chinese
trying to manage it trying to antidote
it trying or just acting out those
senses sense objects
uh just holding views
in regard to it what should be done what
the practice is what i must do
to get rid of it but
all of that is exactly rooted if i don't
do that then what reveals is the pure
pressure pure pressure arisen on its own
and in itself that's a liberating
recognition yeah it is not you realize i
don't need to do anything that's why the
weight the burden is not on you anymore
pressure's there yet it requires no
management no getting rid of no
responding to this or that you're on
account of the dharma practice that you
believe in all the views about
the pressures there
all you need to do is not welcome it and
not delight it and it's not your problem
you want to reveal you want to you want
to reveal its nature
so to speak because nature of whatever
appears because it appears that's why it is
because it appears that's why it is
uncertain that's why it's impermanent
that's why it cannot be yours even if
you want it to be yours so if you
actually are able
to endure it on that right level clearly
enough without giving into it that
nature will become apparent oh whatever
has the nature of horizon has the nature
of ceasing i don't need to do anything
and that's how you basically
discern what a practice is what the
middle way is
and that's how you you you are not
affected personally you know you don't
so i remove myself from this taking
things personally well
yeah it's not a matter of choice yes
you're still people can have the idea
about it
but it's what it would have said like
with their self they're practicing
outside so you have to undo that self
identity indirectly to
indirectly to
seeing the nature of what is
pressuring what is presently pressuring you
what is presently pressuring you
the body the feelings
by seeing the nature that self is
dissolving so to speak in the background yeah
so to speak in the background yeah
that there is nobody that is now
pressuring but pleasure has to be devalued
but pleasure has to be devalued
because until it is one will still
uh well it will be
acting it will be devalued if you stick
to this
of course because you obviously i mean
because that's the reason why
i act in such a way yeah that's why i
want to get rid of this pleasure exactly
yeah so
so
the only way to devalue it is to
take it on faith first that it's worth
going against him
and then it will become apparent that
yes it is dangerous it's not really
pleasurable uh and then you will stop valuing it but
uh and then you will stop valuing it but
if you expect
the the devaluing of it to become
apparent before you take it on faith and
start practicing in that direction no
you have to meet it halfway basically
it's not going to happen otherwise
this idea of a peaceful death
you know someone can have a peaceful
death he died peacefully
look at him
you know it's obvious it was peaceful
the angels came and
took him up to heaven or something
as a so
and you can so you can imagine i think
if anyone had to think about it really
what if you know you lose that
movement of your arm you can't you have
a stroke how does that feel
internally you have no you know you're
not not a practitioner
you can't speak you've got all these
desires how's that gonna feel
peaceful for you you might look peaceful
you know but really
how internally is that going to feel
good pleasant no
no
it's a guy
it's going to be intense
so that is where you are headed you know
but not to play devil's advocate
somebody who has been following our
discussion so far
might also say i just continue living my
life like i do and things become too
painful i just take a bunch of
sleeping pills or painkillers i just
overdose trip out
hoping to not experience the pain of
death and that's it so why would i even make
and that's it so why would i even make
an effort to go through all of this
enduring and everything that is bound up with it
and everything that is bound up with it
um
somebody who is like skeptical or
cynical might think like that and not
see the problem
yeah so i think they fall into the
fourth category of people whether they
hear them be tore down it makes no
difference they're not gonna change the
waves like a dead horse doesn't matter
how much you flog it it's not gonna get
up
some people will practice if they get
the point
some people will practice regardless if
they hear it or not
but then you have people that even if
they hear the purest damage coming from
the buddha still won't agree won't see
it and we'll dismiss it
so if the level of cynicism is there if
they don't even see the problem if they
think just ending their life is a
solution well
they still have they have plenty of uh
work to do before they can even begin to
consider the dharma
as in work in terms of clearing up their
reasoning and beliefs
they're obviously based on their senses
and then you know the buddha's doctrine
of rebirth clearly indicates that you
know taking your own life does not
actually solve the problem yeah but if
somebody's as cynical as you presented
it
to you quoting some views and rebirth by
some authority as far as they're
concerned then that's not going to
change your mind
what would change your mind is to racuna
is that
as much as they can dismiss the rebirth
they can also dismiss that the death is
the end because they don't know either
so what if it isn't and so is it worth
the risk basically ask yourself that if
you're that cynical is it worth the risk
because if you were wrong and death is
not the end or you really shot yourself
in the foot there
so is it worth the risk because what you
have to lose here
if you behave and develop some sense
restraint and a bit of composure
um nothing you're just gonna gain even
in this life so it would be a win-win
but um yeah
it takes takes transparency takes a
person individually needs to make an
effort in their direction no matter what
you tell them
if they're looking for faults and
justifications doesn't matter i mean
the buddha himself was number of times
just dismissed
because people don't want to hear it specifically practice
specifically practice
mindfulness of death
the the the sign of death or the image
or the phenomena or the dharma
or the background or the context or the
significance and there are many ways to
describe um
it's more general um
i mean it's it's
yeah i mean it's incredibly
general in the sense that yeah any
action one
does is within this context of
the fact that one will die so
so it is your enclosure basically
becoming established in that image or
that dharma or that
yeah as long as as long as a person is
not attempting to access that image
directly and attend to it as an object
yeah exactly because it's not it's
always the background of your current
situation so how'd you find it
in your current situation yeah then you
recognize the liability that that
current situation is enclosed within has
to be the presently enduring experience
in order for it to
be
authentic
but isn't there a problem with death
that it's in
tanya said an inferior experience it's
not part of my of the pathogenous
actual experience it always is in fear
from seeing other people no no that's
idea of death is inferred
but because of that inauthenticity
because he basically projects himself
into this public world of others whereby
i observe things with my senses thus
that's what my senses are
but if he were to recognize that there
is a inherent problem logical problem
with that approach
he would recognize that okay so i cannot
directly attend to death and experience
it beforehand as an object of my
experience because it's what my
experience is under my body so then you
recognize the liability the possibility
the danger the parallel of that
situation and still you can't fix that
all you can do is abandon that which is
liable to it abandon your experience
in total and that's how you know you'll
be on death not because you experienced
it beforehand and then you learned about
it
so the problem for tujina is
even when he thinks about death he's put
himself first
putting his point of view that infers or
examines death externally that point of
view is first death is second
now you can learn about it theoretically
in that way but if you are transparent
and you have practiced the right
reasoning you realize right but it's my
very point of view that thinks about
death that is already undermined by
death and that's how you get to see the
and that's how you get to see the
background that i talk about you can't
attend to it directly because then it's
a foreground
so within the presently enjoying
experience whatever i'm thinking or seeing or
whatever i'm thinking or seeing or
hearing or tasting or touching
peripheral to that experience or
there is
there is death there yeah and what what
would the uh kind of
signs and features this practical no no
what would the practical signs and
features of that death be
of that phenomenon of that liability the
background liability that everything
could end outside of my control
and nothing i do conceive do
conceive infer whatever else
i i revolve around none of that can
actually take me outside of that that
that as i said enclosure that is sort of
displeasure i mean this pleasure okay
what else
what would be the signs and features of
that of that
kind of all kind of despair
despair well yeah but that's more like
your uh well that's more like the reaction of
uh well that's more like the reaction of
the mind that's not developed but just
purely liability of death or the background of
liability of death or the background of
death let's put it like that
what what is one of the what is the main
what is one of the what is the main
characteristic of that what's the main
property arisen by itself i mean what's the main
arisen by itself i mean what's the main
property of things that have arisen by
themselves on their own
on their own
exactly
that's it's the uncertainty that's it
those those eyes that body
that's all uncertain inaccessible to me
yeah so i'm enclosed to that
disintegrating thing that thing that's
changing and that uncertainty encloses
me when i think outside of it that's
already within that uncertainty
there is no outside of it
so that's why that other talk with it
basically if you train your mind towards
the ultimate uncertainty
so you stop resisting it trying to get
rid of it trying to antidote it trying
to uh or act out of it welcoming delight
in it to photos distraction from it and
so on
that uncertainty that you will train
your mind in regard to to become
dispassionate and not averse towards or
afraid from is nibana
the ultimate uncertainty that's it
that's the phenomenon of nirvana
here and now
and then if you have developed your mind
towards that background phenomenon of
uncertainty is absolutely nothing
that can that can disturb the mind
that comes second basically
there's no room for any kind of
suffering whatsoever impossible because
any suffering
any dukkha is always because of a nature
any suffering is always because of
uncertainty or more specifically because
of ignoring a certainty appropriating
uncertainty contradicting uncertainty
contradicting uncertainty
trying to outrun get rid of manage
uncertainty that's the dukkha
so if you understand nietzsche you get
that
you pick up the sign of the nature and
you are
thereby you realize how enclosed you are
within that
nature that will feel like pressure yeah like a
that will feel like pressure yeah like a
choking a strangling of yourself
not necessarily i'm enclosed within each
other initially yes and
for different people to different
degrees but really the pain of it will
be determined on by how much you're
resisting it they're trying to outrun it
how how undeveloped your mind is
developed mind the mind of composure the
mind of somalia is the one that doesn't
tremble in the face of things they would want to
in the face of things they would want to
kind of shake you up as they so to say
and centrist and virtue yeah that's very
valuable yeah that's samadhi already
that's that's the beginning of a samadhi
it's not like concentration of sort of
focusing on one point where the whole
context everything disappears no no
quite the opposite it means the ultimate
context of like uncertainty death stuff
that you cannot possibly i mean you can
be not sure but you cannot step outside
of that doesn't shake the mind anymore
it does not compromise the composure
mind remains composed within that
just that image of you know being
captioning enclosed
maybe strangling available
yeah it might feel like strangling if
you you know at first but self gets kind
of suffocating and
dissolving that self
identity because
you there is you know the whole
experience is
inaccessible outside
you're just here secondary
nothing is yours they're solutions
they're solutions
buried alive yeah
it's like
that's also why
the contemplation of death i was
thinking something you say i've heard you say in
something you say i've heard you say in
regards to contemplating anita is that
you have to find things that are dear to
you and contemplate their
and contemplate their
change loss destruction
but that's why
that's why
contemplation of death correctly
basically sort of includes anything
the loss the change of the anything that
is implicit to be exactly it's included
within us whereas the most
because you know you can pick something that's
you know you can pick something that's
dear to you um one thing and already
that's you know for somebody who hasn't
done it at all
it's already sort of disturbing to think
about it's it's if it's mine it's dear
to me
um
but usually then
you don't even think about losing the
things that are so close to you that
they're so dear to you that they are
what you what make you what you are
and so
the only thing that would do that is
thinking about dying
um
but like
like
even that as we spoke before in the
previous video that that um the edge of
it would kind of wear off
yeah and it's like oh why is that or
have you fulfilled the contemplation of
that system or edge or are you on the
other hand it's like oh no because
you're doing it at the arm's length now
you might have felt it initially and
that arm's length distance will be
created if your senses have not been
restrained well enough if you have not
been um like seeing the danger in the
um like seeing the danger in the
slightest fault and everything else that
it says because in other words even if
you don't actively contemplate death by
actually saying no to the sensible
keeping the virtue solitude you are
contemplating that yeah
you might not specifically
discern that as a as a theme as a
background of your day-to-day life but you are
of your day-to-day life but you are
doing it you are there but it is the
same with like mindfulness of the body
of course
yeah yeah treating it as not yours
as uncertain
because that's what it is you know you
you're not giving in to those pressures
anymore you're acting
you're acting
in the right way
yeah by not acting out of it yeah but if
you act out of it try to manage that now
you you possess trying to possess
you possess trying to possess
appropriate forgetting
yeah forgetting that and that's that's
like again it's hard for people to
it's hard for people to hear and it's
even harder to give up that that that
need of management that's kind of um
that dharma is misconceived as
so basically people approach dharma
practice as a way of helping them manage
the pain that's not a dhamma that's
management dharma uproots the pain
completely makes you unliable to it
anymore but that's hard see you really need to
but that's hard see you really need to
give up any idea of your escape
outside of what you're enclosed with in
order to discern where true escape is
so
you need to basically take on the pain
first in the sense of
not acting out of it not not not
welcoming distractions or sensuality not
trying to get rid of it either and
that's when you will also realize how
deeply rooted craving against pain is
like you have the for example the
experience of anxiety which is just the
experience of uncertainty
how many people have developed their
mind that they can
endure that anxiety
without acting out of it without
justifying it psychologizing it without
doing the dharma as a response to it can
just be unmoved by it
now many because they will require
serious development of the mind on the
level of you have now thoroughly
understood the root of the action your
intentions and the craving behind and
the reason why people come because the
craving to get rid of the ultimate
discomfort of uncertainty i anxiety is
just too much to bear
so yes it will be too much to bear but
that is the goal that's what you need to
train for
that removing that resistance not
removing anxiety
uncertainty remains
things have been uncertain and remain
uncertain what has changed is the level
of resistance
to discomfort of uncertainty
and that's amadi
and that is safety
so you develop that type of
uh context recognition and composure in
face of that
that is nibana here and now nothing can
move you
it's even just
like what you said the
the mindfulness is
is even just recognizing let's say just
the body the fact that um
you don't need to think about
death even specifically
but um
the fact that the body is there and it's
already just something that is
there on its own in a way that is
you have no
choice about it no say in it nothing you
can you didn't um choose it create it
doesn't it's not unaffected by
anything that you could do or
read like what whether whether the
buddha says that the body is there or
not the body you're still kind of within
it
it's almost as
it feels almost that same sense of
anxiety or it feels like something you're
or it feels like something you're
enclosed within
and almost as much as
almost as much as
the
idea of being liable to death as in it's
just something that is totally
inaccessible to you in a way
yeah well that's
well that's
that's that's what that is the extent of
the body is the extent
the extent of the enclosure
and it's something that
you cannot help
knowing in a way like it's not
yeah i see what you mean you cannot help
um
you cannot know in a direct sense
because you cannot become the object of
yourselves but you can discern it
but you can discern it
like in that
science the necessary signs and features of that
the necessary signs and features of that
but in order to discern it you need to
stop going down the
kind of directions and baits that sense
is set up for you
so see by going after sense objects you
have already taken up implicitly the
sense organs you have taken up the body
even if you say i contemplate the known
body and each and death no
you're still aiming at
the sense objects including you know
thoughts of management and views and so
on means you are taking up the body
you haven't truly allowed that enclosure
of your situation to become apparent
because that's unpleasant
yeah i mean
yeah that's kind of what what i meant
that the body even the fact that the
body is alive is almost as dangerous as
the fact that the the body will die or is it
fact that the the body will die or is it
is as bad
as as as a nietzsche yeah that's where
the danger is exactly because you're not
that that's exactly exactly
what that's what the danger is
so without right view there's no
alternative to
management the difference between
managing and uprooting
is a practice after the rights
yeah basically yeah
management is when there is no right
view
in other words you're still revolving
around same principles of aversion towards pain
same principles of aversion towards pain
delight and pleasure
you said yesterday what was the closest
what can you do then
and in a way you can do the right
viewing you just do that yeah do the right view
you just do that yeah do the right view
how do you do that well by not doing all
sorts of other things
well that is like you know when you say
master gautama
like no they would have said first oh if
i if i fought the waves i timed myself
out and if i stood still i sang
so master gautama how did you then cross
the the wild river across to the other
side by not fighting the waves by not
standing still so like okay so what do
you do then
well that's what you do
not doing things that are rooted in
green division delusion including your
idea of doing the practice
and that the more you commit to
discerning that context and intentions
where they're rooted the clearer this
middle way of
non-doing well the clearer the doing of
the middleweight which is the way of
non-doing becomes apparent
but now you can just jump the queue as
we said yesterday
and mystify this non-doing of the middle
way and then just abstain no no no the
problem's still there so that's why like
you should not tolerate your situation
that hasn't been resolved liability to
death is still there sensuality is still
there and you're just quoting the end
result of yes arahant has gone beyond
duty and is nothing so there is no doing
okay but it takes some serious doing in
order to get there doing of what well
doing of sense restraint principle doing
of not welcoming doing of non-managing
so doing of certain non-doings that's
what's required
and clarifying the right order
yeah see that comes with the right view
holding it
investigating intentions
yeah i think that's like probably
i mean we said that before um
the most like the most practical thing
that in terms of you know
contemplation and thinking about of
course you know keeping the presets
first vienna and so on but then yes like
not just take for granted what you
should do or you shouldn't why am i
doing it that is the root of the problem
like things that are rooted in the
intentions of greed aversion delusion
and that uh you know rooted in aversion
towards discomfort
rooted in in delight towards pain
that's why i say like often people's
meditation practices end up revolving on
the same principles as they should say
meditating with sensuality if you don't
have the right view you are meditating
with sensuality whether you know what
sensuality is or not doesn't matter
because why you're doing it because you
still delight in the idea of pleasure
or you're doing it because you're still
delighting the idea of averse towards
pain avoiding the discomfort mental
emotional discomfort
and that's why you won't be doing it
right now that'll also
that'll also
would require
to see this
there's nothing that you have to do as
in everything that you're doing is
really your choice that it's not
because even that is not something that
i used to really realize that there was
a lot there'd be lots of things that i
would do just because i assume duty
duty
yeah exactly that's exactly what that
virgin duty is
you wouldn't if you discerned the sign
of death or body or feeling you just
wouldn't yeah
crave i mean that that's a sign if
you're if you're yeah craving is
incompatible with that context yeah yeah
so if you if you find yourself yeah
angry or yeah or lustful
you will still be able to maintain
perspective okay i haven't clearly
discerned them death in this moment
so what's going on why why hasn't that
yeah well there's i think that dumber
part of us isn't it
says yes corals basically
yes corals basically
are fueled and maintained by the ones
that forget that we are all
condemned like in prison within death subject to
like in prison within death subject to
death
if you don't forget that you will be
unable to quarrel
you just going to the extent of quarrel
and fighting will become inconceivable
because you just see the the enclosure
of this whole situation mine annuals
yeah in that sense and
yes it is incompatible with it yeah yeah the
yeah the
idea of enclosure
and you know there's four great mountains
you know there's four great mountains
coming that's what
the body is it's just disintegrating and
crushing slowly slowly basically seeding
i'm not afraid of death
yet these things are it's
i don't have to worry about something
you know someone coming to kill me
because this thing
is already
crushing and coming to kill me so oh
there is no really you know specific
fear because the whole thing is doing
that anyway my body
anyone as you said before can put
themselves in a room
lock the door and see how that feels
just that you can still move your body
but now you you your closure is a bit
smaller
it's not so bad when you got this
massively close you know it feels very
big you've got space yeah that's that's
all people need to do really just say no
to distractions and
um
seclusion and yeah that's it the
enclosure is going to become
much more obvious revealed yeah
where there is birth this
there is the manifestation there is the
enclosure because that's what's manifested
because that's what's manifested
there is death
disintegrating i like it disintegrating
it's just
aging [Music]
[Music]
but it really is like the ultimate
sign of dukkha in a way that the
this every action that you do in the life is
every action that you do in the life is
determined by needing to
avoid uh
unpleasant things and looking for
pleasant things but now you just have
been thought for anybody
whether you practice or not that there
is this
death coming it's it's it's unpleasant
you can't really if you if you really
think about it seriously you can't be
indifferent to it
and here is this thing that you can't
do something to get rid of it or go
against it yeah because that's exactly
what the king said exactly said what did
you what would you do if i tell you a
mountain coming from the left well i'll
go right
from the right while i go left from the
north from the east and say well what if
they're coming from all four directions
well but you can't move away from it
what would you do then oh then i would
practice the dumb i said well i'm
telling you there are four mountains
coming from every direction
so
it's unmanageable
you can't outrun it you can't get rid of
it you cannot manage it so better stop
managing it while you still have an
option to see it rightly before it's too close
to see it rightly before it's too close
that's the point
and then the the the pain of not giving
in to managing it will be dampened
will will result in composure in samadhi
if you keep your virtue sense restraint
you know moderation seeing the danger in
the slightest fault the pain won't be as
bad but it has to happen
how much of that pain has to happen well
depends how much you resist it and how
much of your virtue has not been
developed sensory strain has not been
developed danger in the sin that the
engineer slices for has not been
developed but it's it's the one way only
but it's it's the one way only
there's no other option no for some
people that one way will be very
unpleasant and slow for somebody will be
very unpleasant but quick for some
people will be not unpleasant but slow
and not unpleasant and very quick
but it's the same way
not various options
various options
because it's really a
just it's something you cannot
it's something you cannot
manage
it's i remember having that
i remember having that
before i knew about the dhamma um
just that
when you think really okay i'm actually
going to die
and i remember even consciously thinking
i cannot keep thinking about this
because i'm literally going to go mad if
i i have to
but yes
i was trying to convince my parents and
like all my friends and they were just
like no it's fine it's fine i was like
banana no seriously then you convinced
yourself
i'm not gonna forget this yeah
no
like if you don't as i said you know
and see that recognition in itself say
oh that's a problem
would be enough for somebody to take
buddha's teaching on faith in terms of
okay i'll i will be restrained i will
keep the precepts i don't necessarily
see immediate benefit from it but
they do offer solution to the problem
the ultimate uncertainty
and if you are kind of doing it rightly in
if you are kind of doing it rightly in
that sense if you stop just trying to
manage it and paste the views of what
the what's happening and what you're
doing and what you're responding and see
it for what it is then you actually do
realize okay there is a way out of this
not by
removing the
the the context of death that i'm in
removing the enclosure but by removing
my resistance towards it
my gratuitous sort of aversion towards
that that's it remove the aversion and
you are free
and that's when like often the the
practices of people meditation
techniques managements are just other
ways of perpetuating aversion
towards discomfort or perpetuating
delight towards the prospect of future
pleasure so he needs to be given up